Guide to the Ireland House Oral History Collection AIA.030
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- M
  - Mulcahy, Denis, Aug 3, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Denis Mulcahy (b. Channel Islands, UK, 1944), retired NYPD bomb squad detective, emigrated to the United States from Cork. He is the founder of Project Children, a program that has fostered peace since 1975 by mixing Catholic and Protestant young people from Northern Ireland together during a stress-free summer in the United States.
  - Mulvihill, James, Nov 7, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Jim Mulvihill (b. 1931) retired as Principal Investigator, Office of the Attorney General of the State of New York in 1995. The son of emigrants from Co. Kerry, he was also Master Paymaster of the Old Guard of the City of New York.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PCM660. The interview is approximately 100 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place in New York City on November 7, 2008, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Murphy, Sr. Bernice, Apr 8, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Sr. Bernice Murphy (b. Castleisland, Co. Kerry, Ireland, 1917), a Missionary Franciscan Sister, taught in Boston, Minnesota and Brooklyn after emigrating to the United States during World War II.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 40 minutes long, on 1 CD. The interview took place in Tenafly, New Jersey, on April 8, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Murphy, Christina, Jul 20, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Christina Murphy (b. Newark, New Jersey) is a Senior Director of Learning and Development for Century 21 Real Estate, and teaches in the Graduate School of Business at Touro College of New York. She is active in New Jersey with the Friends of Erin Scholarship program in Kearney and the Nutley Irish American Alliance.
  - Murphy, James, Feb 6, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    James Murphy, Ph.D. (b. 1940), was born in Brooklyn to 1920s immigrants from Mayo and Leitrim, Ireland. Jim attained his Ph.D. at Temple University and he initiated the Irish Studies program at Villanova University, where he still teaches.
    Some key themes discussed in this interview include: Murphy's aunt who lived on Staten Island who had no contact with other 9 Murphy siblings who were in New York, and it was only her son who ‘discovered’ the family in recent years; the jump from generations of farmers to his dad (a truck salesman) to Jim, a PhD; Irish versus Irish America; a lovely anecdote of his blind cousin ‘seeing’ the Murphy home-place on a 1995 family reunion trip back to Ireland; talks about his grandparents being disconnected from family networks by the emigration of so many of their children; class aspirations of his aunts (‘lace curtain’) and his mother; how Joyce was familiar to Jim when he first read it (track 4); and the dominant role of the Church when he was coming up- he was in a seminary for 2 years.
    This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz PMD660. The interview is approximately 135 minutes long, on 2 CDs. The interview took place in New York City on February 6, 2009, and the interviewer was Myriam Nyhan.
  - Murphy, James (Jim), Oct 19, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Mr. Murphy discusses a range of topics, beginning with his parents’ background and his childhood in the 1960s and 1970s in Queens, New York. Murphy briefly describes his experience as a student at Our Lady of Lourdes, a Catholic grammar school in Queens. He discusses his education at Regis High School, a full scholarship Jesuit institution in Manhattan. During high school, he began an internship at WPIX (now the CW11), where he learned to write and produce news segments under such figures as Dan Doherty. Murphy explains that after high school graduation, he attended classes at Queens College, but he dropped out at the age of 19 to continue working full-time at the station.
    In 1981, Murphy moved to WABC where he became the producer of the Six O'Clock Eyewitness News with news anchor Roger Grimsby, who became one of Murphy’s close friends. He also met Adrienne Barr at WABC, whom he would marry in 1986. Murphy relates that after he left WABC, he moved to WCBS, Channel 2, where he worked alongside his sister Mary, a street crime reporter at the time. Murphy then discusses his move to the syndicated film criticism program Siskel & Ebert & the Movies. Murphy describes how he and his new wife juggled their personal and professional lives after his move to Chicago. He explains that in 1993, he decided to return to New York City and to broadcast journalism because he missed the newsroom.
    Murphy discusses some of his experiences while working at CBS. He talks about the September 11th attacks on the World Trade Center and his experience working as executive producer for the Evening News in the days following the attack. He also discusses his involvement in the first network news broadcasts from Afghanistan after the fall of the Taliban. Murphy also explains how he helped CBS secure an important interview with former Israeli Prime Minister Ariel Sharon, during which Sharon announced a drastic policy change to break relations with former Palestinian President Yasser Arafat. Finally, Murphy highlights some of the bigger moments of his career, including the day he and Rather interviewed Saddam Hussein just weeks before the outbreak of the Iraq War in 2003. He describes the surreal circumstances when he met Saddam Hussein. Murphy also shares his conversation with Rather and Hussein following the interview, in which Hussein expressed his amazement with American political and media strategies. Finally, Murphy talks about returning to Iraq after the Americans began their occupation, and he describes the changing landscape of Iraq.
    Murphy then explains that he left CBS in 2005, following Dan Rather’s departure. He talks about taking a job at ABC’s Good Morning America in 2006, where he currently serves as the senior executive producer, working with anchorwoman Diane Sawyer. Murphy describes the personalities and professional capabilities of anchors such as Rather and Sawyer.
    In the course of the interview, Murphy elaborates on his personal life, discussing his Irish identity, his departure from the Church, and his family history, touching upon his father’s isolated and abusive personality. He talks about visiting Ireland in the 1960s, the 1970s, and in more recent years. Murphy discusses how the economy in Ireland has transformed the country in the past few decades, and how the Celtic Tiger has affected his own family in Ireland. He reflects on the importance of his Irish identity but also on his tendency not to join Irish fraternal organizations.
    The small remainder of the interview focuses on his current job at Good Morning America. Murphy discusses the nature of morning news and his program’s fierce competition with the Today Show.
    The Interview is 1 hour and 40 minutes long. Jim Murphy was interviewed on 19 October 2007 at Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by Sarah O’Hare and Linda Dowling Almeida.
    James (Jim) Murphy (b. 1960), senior executive producer of Good Morning America, ABC's morning news show, is the son of immigrants and the brother of television news reporter, Mary Murphy.
  - Murphy, Joseph, Feb 19, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Murphy, Judy, Feb 19, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Judy Murphy (b. Ballinamore Bridge, Co. Galway, 1938) came to the United States from Rome, where she had been training to become a Franciscan nun. She left religious life and settled in New York in 1957 where she worked in banking. Her husband is Joe Murphy.
  - Murphy, Liam, May 29, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Murphy, Mary, Nov 14, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Mary Murphy (b. 1959), Emmy-award winning television reporter, currently the weekend anchor of the CW11 News at Ten (New York) and correspondent for the “Fact Finders”, a crime investigative team consisting of herself and fellow reporter Peter Thorne on the CW-11, is the daughter of immigrants and the brother of Jim Murphy, senior executive producer of Good Morning America.
  - Murphy, Maureen, Oct 23, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Murphy, Sr. Regina, Nov 9, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Sister Regina Murphy discusses many aspects of her life, beginning with her parents’ immigration to America and her childhood in Riverdale, New York. She details the occupations her parents held as new arrivals in America – her mother a live-in maid and her father a clerk in a grocery store. When her parents wed her father quickly bought out a grocery store, and her mother stopped domestic work and assisted in the store.
    Sister Regina Murphy reviews her childhood – she received religious education throughout her life, attending St. Margaret’s School in Riverdale for primary education, New York, Sacred Heart of Mary High School, and two years at Marymount College in Tarrytown before she entered the convent. She stresses that her religious education during those formative years greatly influence her decision to enter the convent.
    Sister Regina Murphy discusses her decision to enter the convent, against the wishes of her parents. Four years earlier, her older brother Tommy joined the brothers. He would leave before taking final vows, but at the time she entered the convent in 1959, he was still with the brothers. She declares that the only time she remembers her father using profanity was when she told him she wanted to enter the convent. In a similarly vehement reaction, her mother tore up her acceptance letter to the Sisters of Charity, and it was only upon further inquiry with the order that Sister Regina Murphy learned she had been accepted. Although her parents did not initially accept her vocation, Sister Regina Murphy says she felt truly called to enter the convent. She recalls that she was especially stirred at the prospect of doing missionary work.
    Sr. Murphy describes her first foreign mission was to the Bahamas. She worked in education, but during her tenure, she noticed the stark difference between the lives of the native poor and the tourists who visited the Bahamas. This started her personal quest for a better understanding of social justice principles. She talks about her appointment as Mission Coordinator for the order, and how she was able to visit missions in Guatemala. She recalls meeting with a fellow sister named Barbara Ann Ford, who was influential in creating water projects in the poor villages and who participated in The Recovery of Historical Memory project organized by Bishop Juan Geraldi to collect the stories of the survivors and victims of the civil war in Guatemala. Part of the project included providing mental health service for those who were affected by the rampant violence and crime that accompanied the war. Sr. Barbara was shot and killed in 2001 under suspicious circumstance, however her work in Guatemala helped many and also influenced Sister Regina Murphy.
    She describes how her experiences in the Bahamas and Guatemala along with the coming of Vatican II sparked an awakening in her. She saw the changes enacted as part of Vatican II as an energizing and necessary force in the Church. It seemed to her that religious work evolved from seeking to help individuals on a day to day basis to fixing the societal infrastructure responsible for basic injustices. These realizations propelled Sister Regina Murphy to become involved in justice, peace, and corporate responsibility projects.
    When advocating for corporate responsibility, Sister Regina Murphy describes her integral role in the implementation of the McBride Principles and the enactment of the Fair Employment Act in Northern Ireland in 1988. As part of the Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility, she traveled to Northern Ireland in the hopes of getting factories to sign onto the McBride Principles. She recalls that the ICCR was successful in obtaining the signatures of fifty companies. While Sister Regina Murphy was in one General Motors Factory in Northern Ireland, she talks about how her presence caused a temporary strike and shutdown of the factory. Although she was not dressed in a traditional habit, workers guessed that she was a Catholic nun. Seeing her discuss workplace issues with managers in the factory upset the predominately Protestant workers, inciting them to walk off the job. Despite this fervor against the McBride Principles, it was her support, along with that of the ICCR, that she says helped to pass the Fair Employment Act.
    Sister Murphy talks about the current state of vocations in the Church and what she sees for the future of the convent. She describes her life today as a religious woman – what it means to her and what her Irish identity means. She ends the interview talking about her job as property manager for the order, acting as general contractor on major construction projects for the order
    This oral history with Sister Regina Murphy was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview took place on 9 November 2007 at Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by Julia Ryan and Linda Dowling Almeida. The interview is 2 hours, 47 minutes long, on 2 CDs and had been logged at ten minute intervals.
    Sr. Regina Murphy (b. 1939), the property manager for the Sisters of Charity of New York and an advocate for corporate responsibility, fought hard to establish the McBride Principles.
- N
  - Naughton, Frank, Mar 18, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Frank Naughton (b. Manhattan, New York, 1939), a Professor and former Chairperson of Sociology at Kean University in New Jersey, was President of the New York Irish History Roundtable. His father was raised in Cahir, Co. Tipperary from age 6 to 19.
  - Nolan, Mary B., Mar 8, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    Mary B. Nolan (b. Kilfinny, Co. Limerick, Ireland, 1937) is a long-time resident of Brooklyn who became involved in many Irish organizations after emigrating to New York City in 1953.
- O
  - O'Brien, Jack, Mar 22, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Jack O'Brien (b. Hoboken, New Jersey, 1928) played fife for the Jefferson Street Hoboken Playground Band, New York World's Fair Champions in 1939. In 2002 he was inducted into the New Jersey Drum Corps Hall of Fame. He has also taught classes at New York University's Tisch School of the Arts.
  - O'Callaghan, Patricia, Nov 2, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Ms. O’Callaghan discusses a variety of topics beginning with her family and childhood in Cork, Ireland and what life was like growing up on a farm. After obtaining a Bachelor of Arts in English, French and Sociology at the University of County Cork, she moved to Dublin to pursue a Higher Diploma in Education at Trinity College. In Dublin she was given the chance to teach inner-city kids, a far cry from the one room school house she attended as a child. She describes returning to Cork to work for Cork Local Radio as a news presenter. Wanderlust led her to answer an ad in the newspaper for a job marketing Irish hand-crafts in San Francisco, California. Ms. O’Callaghan was handed an H-3 Visa to live in what describes as a fantasy life in the United States, an experience that was somewhat different from the lives of the people she helped later in life.
    She talks about how she turned a temporary stay into a permanent move after she left California for New York to work as a flight attendant for Transamerica Airlines. Reintegrating the Irish back into her life, she became involved with Adrian Flannelly’s Irish radio talk show. She describes how the growing number of undocumented Irish in the mid-1980s led Adrian Flannelly to discuss solutions with the Archdiocese of New York. The talks led to the formation of Project Irish Outreach within the Catholic Charities division of the archdiocese, under the supervision of Monsignor James Murray.
    Asked to help with the project’s establishment, Ms. O’Callaghan found a real purpose in helping the undocumented. She wrote a small booklet titled Immigrating USA: A Guide for Irish Immigrants to answer immigrants frequently-asked questions. Project Irish Outreach had a great impact on Ms. O’Callaghan and the Irish community and she discusses at length the work that the project was able to do through community outreach, immigration and social services, and partaking in efforts to inform people of their rights. The program became a social worker network in a number of fields.
    She recalls the mobilization of the Irish American community along with various other social service and legal organizations during the 1980s, also noting the always positive attitude that Americans, especially New Yorkers, have had towards the Irish.
    While discussing the way her position and role within Catholic Charities has diversified and evolved, Ms. O’Callaghan explains the transformation of Project Irish Outreach since its establishment in 1987. She expresses the many ways in which immigration and the immigrants themselves have changed over time, including the complexity of the immigration system and the choices available to immigrants and emigrants. She delves into the hurdles that the undocumented and documented have to face and the ways the immigration system and legislation can evolve to fit the needs of the immigrant population.
    She closes with describing the strength of the Irish community and the people that have affected her life through her work and what her Catholic and Irish identities mean to her.
    Patricia O’Callaghan was interviewed on 2 November 2007 at Glucksman Ireland House at New York University by Katie Hiebert, Linda Dowling Almeida, and Joe Ready. This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. The interview is 1 hour, 41 minutes long, on two CDs and had been logged at ten minute intervals.
    Patricia O'Callaghan (b. 1951 Cork City, Ireland). She emigrated to San Francisco and has become an advocate for immigratant rights. She has run Project Irish Outreach for 20 years.
  - O'Connor, Patricia Young, May 21, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Patricia Young O'Connor (b. Co. Cork, 1928) became President of the Cork Ladies' Auxiliary of New York in 1960 and served as their delegate to the United Irish Counties Association and to the St. Patrick's Day Parade Committee. She owned a bookstore in Sheepshead Bay, Brooklyn and worked for the Board of Education at Beach Channel High School until retirement.
  - O'Donoghue, Clare, Oct 10, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    Clare O'Donoghue (b. Clonmel, Co. Tipperary, Ireland, 1960) worked as a banker in Ireland, came to Boston in 1992 on a Donnelly visa and works in the health sector.
  - O'Donoghue, Margaret, Jul 8, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Margaret O'Donoghue (b. Limerick City, Ireland, 1960), a psychotherapist and an adjunct professor at the New York University School of Social Work, emigrated to America in 1982 and is raising two children in New Jersey.
  - O'Donoghue, Noreen Lydon, Jan 22, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Noreen Lydon O'Donoghue (b. Tourmakeady, Co. Mayo, 1947), a fluent Irish speaker, emigrated to New York at the age of 16. She has been active in the Irish Immigration Reform Movement and the Emerald Isle Immigration Center in Woodside, Queens since 1988.
  - O'Donovan, Brian, Oct 16, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    Brian O'Donovan (b. Clonakilty, Co. Cork, Ireland, 1957) is host of WGBH radio's 'Celtic Sojourn' and a central figure in the Boston Irish music scene.
  - O'Driscoll, Mae, Nov 18, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    In this interview, O'Driscoll provides detailed information on her childhood in Skibbereen, County Cork, Ireland, including living in rural Ireland and the effects World War II had on her family such as power outages and food rationing. She discusses the options available to her after secondary school at the time and her decision to immigrate to the United States in 1958 to further her education.
    Upon arriving in New York City, O’Driscoll interviewed with the three companies in the city known for hiring large numbers of Irish: the phone company, Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, and Citibank. Within one month of her arrival, O’Driscoll began working at Citibank, a job she kept until 1964. She discusses in detail the discrimination faced by immigrants at the time, including the perception vocalized by an interviewer that the Irish were uneducated. O’Driscoll continues to speak about her early accounting jobs and her eventual hiring at JP Morgan & Co. in 1974.
    In 1975, O’Driscoll enrolled at Brooklyn College and received her Bachelor of Science degree in accounting in 1981. She talks about her decision to return to school and the impact it had on her career. She discusses the discrimination she dealt with as a woman working on Wall Street at the time including being passed over for promotions and eventually having to change departments because of the lack of advancement opportunities open to her.
    Active in the Irish community, O’Driscoll became involved in the Ladies Auxiliary of the Ancient Order of Hibernians (AOH), the National Association for Irish Justice 1969, the Cork Association and in 1989 its first woman president. O’ Driscoll served an integral part in the formation of the Irish Immigration Reform Movement (IIRM) in 1987. She discusses in detail the grassroots efforts of the organization including interaction with legislators and the campaign to raise awareness locally and nationally on the issue and is frank in her assessment of the great obstacles facing the very small group. The IIRM was successful in their efforts in 1990 with the passing of HR-4300, the Immigration Act of 1990. O’Driscoll also speaks about her continued involvement with the Emerald Isle Immigration Center in Woodside, Queens.
    O’Driscoll currently resides in Brooklyn, New York and is still a member of the Cork Association and a trustee and secretary of the Emerald Isle Immigration Center Executive Committee.
    Mae O’Driscoll was interviewed at New York University’s Glucksman Ireland House on 18 November 2005 by Bethany Hartzell and Linda Dowling Almeida. This oral history was digitally recorded on a Marantz CDR420. It is 1 hour, 38 minutes, 27 seconds long, on two CDs, and has been logged at ten minute intervals.
    Mae O'Driscoll (b. 1939), retired Assistant Vice President of the facilities management department for J.P. Morgan Chase, one of the organizers of the Irish Immigration Reform Movement, and a Trustee and Secretary of the Executive Committee of the Emerald Isle Immigration Center.
  - O'Fianghusa, Seamus, Apr 21, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Seamus O'Fianghusa (b. Brooklyn, New York, 1976), the grandchild of immigrants from Counties Limerick and Clare, has Korean ancestry through his mother. A fluent Irish speaker and member of the Donegal Association of New York, he served in Afghanistan with the New York National Guard (69th New York Infantry).
  - O'Hanlan, Terry, Nov 1, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - O'Hara, Mary, Oct 8, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Mary O’Hara was born in Co. Sligo, Ireland, in 1935. A singer and harpist, she became an acclaimed artist in the 1950s and early 1960s. After a twelve-year stint in a monastery, she returned to her passion in 1974 and retired from performing in 1994. Creativity runs in the family; her sister was the well-known actor Joan O’Hara and her nephew is the writer Sebastian Barry.
  - O'Hara, Teresa, Jul 31, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    Teresa O'Hara (b. New York, New York, 1965), co-founder of the Irish Immigration Center, Boston, and a Health Policy specialist. She returned to Ireland to teach, currently at the Athlone Institute of Technology.
  - O'Leary, Stella, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)